<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 -
 -  Developed By:      Intecs  S.P.A.
 -  File Name:         $RCSfile: toolbox.xml,v $
 -  TOOLBOX Version:   $Name: HEAD $
 -  File Revision:     $Revision: 1.3 $
 -  Revision Date:     $Date: 2007/02/13 09:56:40 $
 -
 -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="C:\LOR\toolboxUpgrade.xsl"?>
<toolbox xmlns="http://pisa.intecs.it/mass/toolbox/toolbox" version="6.0">
	<description>
		<abstract>The TOOLBOX has been developed under the SSE project.
					SSE integrates service providers (having variety of component models or middle-ware suited for their different 
					platforms or environments) through XML, i.e. using SOAP and WSDL transported over a variety of transport mechanisms, 
					i.e. IP, HTTP, and HTTPS. Thus, any service to be integrated within the SSE infrastructure must expose a SOAP interface 
					(described by a WSDL file) according to the SSE Interface Control Document (SSE ICD). 
					The TOOLBOX helps the service provider to convert its services in a SOAP based service, leveraging from all coding problems. 
					The real convertion is made by Toolbox executing a user-provided set of script files, through which the legacy service is invoked.
					The only development requested to the final user is to write and provide that set of Toolbox scripts.
					A wide selection of legacy services can be converted by Toolbox thanks to its powerful and always growing scripting language.
		</abstract>
		<newFeatures>
			 <feature>Input and output invalid message are now stored in the log directory and can be inspected. </feature>
             <feature>Added the base64 support: a new tag to encode/decode binary file using base64 has been added. This tag can be used to include binary file in the XML messages. </feature>
             <feature>Modified the file load/store tags: it is now possible to load and store binary files. By default the text mode is used. </feature>
             <feature>Added the binary handling feature in the http tag: it is now possible to download binary files. By default the text mode is used. </feature>
             <feature>Added the throw tag: using this tag it is possible to stop the execution of a script and send an error message to the client. </feature>
             <feature>Updated the instance list page: now it is possible to sort the list in ascending and descending mode. </feature>
             <feature>Added the pagination for the instance list page. Now 20 results per page are displayed. </feature>
			 
			 <feature></feature>
			 <feature>Development Environment integrated in Eclipse IDE for faster and easier TOOLBOX scripts development</feature>
			 <feature>Online forum at <a>http://toolbox.pisa.intecs.it/forum/</a></feature>
		</newFeatures>
		<download>http://toolbox.pisa.intecs.it/download/download.jsp</download>
		<infoPage>http://toolbox.pisa.intecs.it/</infoPage>
	</description>
</toolbox>
